Guide to Amie Karp Collection of Tobacciana 1870-1997 PR 392
New-York Historical Society
Amie Karp collection of tobacciana
1870-1997
New-York Historical Society
Karp, Amie
PR 392
5 Linear feet in 9 boxes
The Amie Karp Collection of Tobacciana consists of a variety of 19th and 20th century tobacco-related ephemera and reference material.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series by format:
Series I: Catalogs
Series II: Ephemera
Series III: Reference Books
Conditions Governing Access
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Amie Karp, 2019
Scope and Contents
The Amie Karp Collection of Tobacciana is mainly comprised of 19th and 20th century tobacco-related ephemera. It includes cigar bands, cigar box labels, tobacco tags, cigarette boxes, cigarette cards, and tobacco pouches. The ephemera is variously mounted on boards, sleeved, and displayed in scrapbooks. The collection also contains printed catalogs advertising cigar and cigarette cards, tags, labels, boxes and bands. Many of the catalogs include instructions for claiming prizes in exchange for these items. Ten reference books about tobacco, tobacco ephemera, and collecting tobacciana are also included.
Related Materials
Additional tobacciana material can be found in the following collections:
PR 31 Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera
PR 241 Sidney Voice Collection of Cigar Bands
PR 264 Ephemera File
Separated Materials
Additional tobacciana material donated by Amie Karp can be found in New-York Historical's museum collections.
Advertising -- Tobacco industry; Cigar bands and labels; Cigar box labels; Cigarette cards; Tobacco -- United States.
- Series I: Catalogs, 1882-1956
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains printed catalogs advertising cigar and cigarette cards, tags, boxes and bands. Many of the catalogs include instructions for claiming prizes in exchange for these items.
  - W. Duke and Co. cigarette card catalog of "Costumes of All Nations", 1882 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Kinney Brothers Standard of the World cigarette card catalog of "National Dances, Vol. IV", 1886 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - O.L. Schwenke cigar box label catalog, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Florodora Tag Company catalog and instructions for redeeming gifts for tobacco tags and cigar bands., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Schulte Cigars and United Profit-Sharing Co. catalog and instructions for securing gifts by coupon redemption, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Raleigh Coupons, Brown and Williams Tobacco Co. catalogs with instructions for redemption of Raleigh cigarette pack coupons for gifts (4), 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Ephemera, 1870-1936
  This series includes cigar bands, cigar box labels, tobacco tags, cigarette boxes, cigarette cards, and tobacco pouches. The ephemera is variously mounted on boards, sleeved, and displayed in scrapbooks.
  - Cigar Bands, 1874-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Cigar bands with imagery including Civil War generals, United States presidents, and international heads of state.
  - Cigar Box Labels A-K, 1874-1935 (Box 2, Folder 2-12)
  - Cigar Box Labels L-Z, 1874-1935 (Box 3, Folder 1-16)
  - Cigar Protectors, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Reliance Cigar Co. box of lithographed, accordion folded, glassine and card stock single cigar protectors for pocket portage. Illustrated on front and back with a burning cigar.
  - Cigarette Boxes, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Kinsman's Asthmatic Cigarettes, 10 empty boxes.
  - Scrapbooks, 1878-1936 (Box 5)
    "Cigar Bands" - two volumes of specialty collector books with slotted pages filled with cigar bands. Both volumes are inscribed "Annie L. Taff" in pen on the inside front cover; one volume is also marked "Fred A. Taff." 1878-1905.
    "White Knight" - child's collection of 420 cigar bands in a notebook, 1900-1906.
    "Estemento Superiores" - a child named Ward Heinzman's collection of 351 cigar bands (along with some postage stamps) in a ledger book, 1908.
    "Wills Cigarette Picture-Card Album of Household Hints," 1936.
  - Tobacco Pouches, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Scotten, Dillon Company "Yankee Girl" chewing tobacco pouches (10).
  - Tobacco Tags, 1870-1930 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    Embossed and printed tin plug tobacco tags on boards.
- Series III: Reference Books, 1969-1997
  This series contains ten reference books about tobacco, tobacco ephemera, and collecting tobacciana.
  - "Connoisseur's Book of the Cigar," by Zino Davidoff, McGraw Hill, New York, NY, 1969 (Box 7)
  - "Tobacco Tin Tags," by Gary Schild, Prentis and Co., Meridien, CT, 1972 (Box 7)
  - "Handbook of Cigar Boxes," by Tony Hyman, Arnot Art Museum, Elmira, NY, 1979 (Box 8)
  - "The Art of the Cigar Label," by Joe Davidson, Wellfleet Press, Secaucus, NJ, 1989 (Box 8)
  - "Chewing Tobacco Tin Tags 1870-1930," by Louis Storino, Schiffer Publishing Co., PA, 1995 (Box 9)
  - "The Good Cigar: the Art of Cigar Smoking," Jeffers and Gordon, Lyons and Burford, New York, NY, 1996 (Box 9)
  - "Old Time Cigar Labels," Carol Belanger Grafton, Dover, New York, NY, 1996 (Box 8)
  - "The Cigar," by Barnaby Conrad III, Chronicle Books, San Francisco, CA, 1996 (Box 8)
  - "Cigar Companion," by Anwar Bati, Running Press, London, UK, 1997 (Box 7)
  - "The Smoking Life," by Ilene Barth, Genesis Press, Birmingham, MS, 1997 (Box 9)